John B. Hart Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics Collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
John B. Hart Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics Collection
1961-2005
1961-1964
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Hart, John B., 1924-2007
2.5 linear feet (6 manuscript boxes and 10.16 GB)
Collection documents the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics, which the Xavier University Department of Physics hosted from October 1-5, 1962. The conference, jointly sponsored by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the Office of Naval Research, and the Judge Robert S. Marx Foundation, was chaired by physics professor Boris Podolsky. John B. Hart served as conference manager. The principal participants were six eminent physicists, including two Nobel Prize winners, who were joined by sixteen other specially invited physicists from around the world. The collection contains conference planning documentation, grant materials, financial records, correspondence, reports, publicity, and photographs. It includes sound recordings of public lectures and transcripts of the conference proceedings. The collection also includes a small amount of papers and lectures on other physics-related topics.
XUA-90
Biography of John B. Hart and History of the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics
John B. Hart (1924-2007) was a professor in the physics department at Xavier University from 1951-1999. Prior to that, he was a graduate assistant and assistant instructor in the department. Hart often chaired the department from 1957-1971 and served as chair again in 1982-1983. Hart was an officer in the United States Navy in World War II and then continued with the United States Navy Reserves for twenty-six years. He earned his bachelor's degree (1944) and master's degree (1950) from Xavier University.
One of Hart's notable accomplishments was being the conference manager for the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics held at Xavier University in October 1962. Boris Podolsky served as conference chair and Frederick Werner as the assistant chair. The conference was the idea of Podolsky, who had been an associate of Albert Einstein at Princeton University and had joined the Xavier physics department in 1961 after teaching at the University of Cincinnati. The purpose of the conference was to examine some of the fundamental issues in the foundations of quantum mechanics, including the Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen Effect, the quantum measurement problem, and to what extent had relative theory and quantum theory been united consistently. The conference had six main participants, two of whom were Nobel Prize winners (P. A. M. Dirac and Eugene Wigner), plus a limited-attendance group of sixteen physicists who met in private sessions. Some conference events on the first two days were open to the general public. Hart also participated in the 40th anniversary commemoration of the conference in 2002.
Not specified
Scope and Content
This collection documents the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics, which the Xavier University Department of Physics hosted from October 1 to 5 in 1962. Materials include conference planning documentation, correspondence, publicity, and photographs. The collection contains sound recordings of public lectures and transcripts of the conference proceedings. In addition, there is also a small amount of papers and lectures on other physics-related topics.
Series I, Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics, 1961-2003, contains conference proposals, grant materials, financial records, correspondence, invitations, registrations, event schedules, publicity, and photographs. Included is a photograph album documenting conference events, most of which took place in Alter Hall or Logan Hall on the campus of Xavier University. There were six main participants: Boris Podolsky, Xavier University; P. A. M. Dirac, Cambridge University (England); Nathan Rosen, Technion (Haifa, Israel), W. H. Furry, Harvard University; Eugene Wigner, Princeton University; and Yakir Aharonov, Yeshiva University. The series contains correspondence from these six and the sixteen other participants including Eugene Merzbacher, William Band, Oldwig von Roos, Solomon Schwebel, Abner Shimony, and Kaiser Kunz. The series also contains sound recordings of public lectures by Dirac, Furry, Wignar, and Aharonov and transcripts of the conference proceedings. While the conference proceedings were not formally published, Dirac's lecture, "The Evolution of the Physicist's Picture of Nature," delivered on the second evening of the conference, was published in Scientific American (May 1963). Frederick Werner published a summary of the conference in Physics Today (January 1964). Both articles are in the collection.
Series II, Physics Publications and Lecture, 1964-2005, contains CDs of a sound recording of a lecture titled, "Projective Geometry: Origin of Quantum Equations" given by Dirac at Boston University on October 30, 1972. The series also includes two papers by Solomon Schwebel that were sent to John B. Hart in 1964.
Statement of Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series: Series I: Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics and Series II: Physics Publications and Lectures.
Related Material
XUA-66, Xavier University Department of Physics records, Xavier University Archives, Xavier University, Cincinnati, Ohio
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research. Due to preservation concerns, original audio reel-to-reel tapes and CDs cannot be used. Contact archives staff for access to digital access copies.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Verna Gibson Hart, 2014 (XUA2016-02)
Publication note
Conference lecture and summary published in:
Dirac, P. A. M. "The Evolution of the Physicist's Picture of Nature." Scientific American, May 1963.
Werner, Frederick. "The Foundations of Quantum Mechanics: A Conference Report." Physics Today, January 1964.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Quantum theory.; Quantum theory--History.; Physics--Study and teaching.; Physics--Research.; Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen experiment
Persons:
Hart, John B., 1924-2007; Podolsky, Boris, 1896-1966; Dirac, P. A. M. (Paul Adrien Maurice), 1902-1984; Werner, Frederick; Rosen, Nathan, -1995; Wigner, Eugene Paul, 1902-1995; Aharonov, Yakir, 1932-; Furry, W. H. (Wendell Hinkle), 1907-1984; Schwebel, Solomon L.
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Department of Physics.
Material Types:
Live sound recordings; Photographic prints
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Series I, Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics, 1961-2003
  - Conference proposal, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Grant materials, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    Contains grant award letters, incoming and outgoing correspondence, financial records, and reports for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration grant, the Office of Naval Research grant, and the award from the Judge Robert S. Marx Foundation. Financial records include budgets, receipts, and expenses.
  - Correspondence, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7-16)
    Contains correspondence from conference organizers and invited guests, including such notable physicists as Niels Bohr, Alfred Lande, P. A. M. Dirac, Eugene Wigner, and Louis de Broglie. Bohr, Lande, and de Broglie declined the invitation. Correspondence discusses such topics as conference funding, travel arrangements, admission tickets, special events, lecture arrangements, and requests for recordings, transcripts, and publications of conference proceedings. The majority of the correspondence is either written by or directed to Hart as conference manager or Podolsky as chair.
  - List of principal participants and biographical information, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes a photocopy of a letter of recommendation written by Albert Einstein to the University of Cincinnati on behalf of Boris Podolsky.
  - Registration forms, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Schedule of events and handouts for participants, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Special events, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    Contains invitations, tickets, and guest lists for special events hosted during the conference.
  - Sound recordings of lectures, 1962 October (Box 6)
    Recordings consist of public lectures given by Aharonov, Furry, and Wigner on the first day of the conference, and by Dirac on the second day.
    Reel-to-reel tapes have been digitized. Access is available in Exhibit, the digital repository of Xavier University Library.
    - On the Significance of Electromagnetic Potentials in the Quantum Domain, 1962 October 1; Aharonov, Yakir, 1932- (Reel XUA90-a01)
    - The Quantum-Mechanical Description of States and Measurements, 1962 October 1; Furry, W. H. (Wendell Hinkle), 1907-1984 (Reel XUA90-a02-01, Reel XUA90-a02-02)
      Lecture is transcribed in the conference transcript available online in Exhibit, the digital repository of Xavier University Library.
    - Concept of Observation in Quantum Mechanics, 1962 October 1; Wigner, Eugene Paul, 1902-1995 (Reel XUA90-a02-02, Reel XUA90-a03)
    - The Evolution of the Physicist's Picture of Nature, 1962 October 2; Dirac, P. A. M. (Paul Adrien Maurice), 1902-1984 (Reel XUA90-a04-01, Reel XUA90-a04-02)
      Lecture is transcribed in the conference transcript available in Exhibit, the digital repository of Xavier University Library.
  - First draft of conference transcript, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3-13)
  - Distribution lists for conference transcript, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Transcript corrections from conference participants, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Conference manuscript, 1962; 2002 (Box 2, Piece 1, Box 3-4, Box 5, Folder 1)
    A transcript of the conference proceedings was created by Frederick Werner from sound recordings of the conference. The recordings used for the transcript are not all represented in the collection. Not everything was transcribed: material previously published, including presentations by Jack Rivers, Solomon Schwebel, and Eugene Guth, was omitted. The transcript includes portions of both the public and closed sessions. Included in the series are copies of the conference manuscript for W. H. Furry, Nathan Rosen, Eugene Merzbacher, and John B. Hart along with corrected and uncorrected drafts in print typescript and on CDs.
    Conference manuscript has been digitized and is available in Exhibit, the digital repository of the Xavier University Library. Digital copies of transcript drafts on CDs exist. Contact archives staff for access.
  - Photograph album of conference activities, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of participants, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Public relations policy, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Publicity, 1962-1994 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - "The Evolution of the Physicist's Picture of Nature," Scientific American, 1963 May (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlets on publishing articles, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 40th anniversary commemoration of the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics materials, 1992-2004; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio) (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Contains 2 CDs of the transcript, which were digitized and converted to Portable Document Format by Joseph Brinkman in 2002. Brinkman corrected most insignificant spelling and grammatical errors but retained an emphasis on recreating the original document, including handwritten notes by the attendees and certain grammatical styles. Transcript includes articles published by Dirac and Werner as well as an introduction written by Hart in 2002.
    Electronic copies of CDs exist. Contact archives staff for access.
- Series II, Physics publications and lectures, 1964-1987
  Series is arranged alphabetically by last name of author.
  - P. A. M. Dirac, Projective geometry: origin of quantum equations lecture, 1972; 2005; Dirac, P. A. M. (Paul Adrien Maurice), 1902-1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Contains CDs of a sound recording made by Hart of Dirac speaking about projective geometry on October 30, 1972 at Boston University. This recording, according to Hart, includes the personal announcement by Dirac that he had never published his "secret" use of projective geometry in creating quantum mechanics. Roger Penrose offers concluding remarks at the end of the recording.
  - Heinz Pagels, Bell's Inequality, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Chapter published in The World of Physics: A Small Library of the Literature of Physics from Antiquity to the Present, volume 2, edited by Jefferson Hane Weaver. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1987.
  - Solomon Schwebel papers, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Includes physics papers written by Schwebel that he sent to Hart in 1964.